Register of the Jan Karski Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Jan Karski papers
1939-2007
46033
Karski, Jan, 1914-2000
19 manuscript boxes, 10 oversize boxes, 6 card file boxes, 24 photo envelopes, and 26 microfilm reels (20 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, memoranda, government documents, bulletins, reports, studies, speeches and writings, printed matter, photographs, clippings, newspapers, periodicals, sound and video recordings, and microfilm, relating to events and conditions in Poland during World War II, the German and Soviet occupations of Poland, treatment of the Jews in Poland during the German occupation, and operations of the Polish underground movement during World War II.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives from 1946 to 2008.
Accruals
Additional materials may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat to find the full extent of the collection.
Alternative Forms of Material Available
Collection is available on microfilm.
Biographical Note
1914 June 24 Born Jan Kozielewski in Lodz
1935 Law student at University of Lwow
1939 Recruited into the Polish diplomatic service Mobilized, September campaign - escapes Soviet imprisonment First mission to the West, France
1940 Second mission - Failed
1942 Smuggled into Warsaw ghetto and a concentration camp to prepare a report on Nazi war crimes Reports on his mission to representatives of governments of Poland and Great Britain
1943 Reports about situation in Poland to President Franklin D. Roosevelt and other U.S. officials
1944 Publishes Story of a Secret State
1952 Receives PhD from Georgetown University
1953 Enrolls at School of Foreign Service, Georgetown University
1954 Naturalized as American citizen. Works for United States Information Service
1965 Marries Pola Nirenska
1984 Retires from Georgetown University
1985 Publishes The Great Powers and Poland
1994 Made honorary citizen of Israel
2000 July 13 Dies in Washington D.C.
Scope and Content Note
Jan Karski, 1914-2000, born Jan Kozielewski, was a Polish liaison officer working for the Polish underground during World War II. He carried the first eyewitness accounts of the Holocaust to a generally unbelieving West.
The process of the deposition of his papers at Hoover began in 1946 and lasted for over sixty years. Herbert Hoover, who was aware of Karski's excellent connections within diplomatic circles, enlisted him in 1945 to collect documents of the Polish Government in Exile, which by that time had lost recognition of all western powers who accepted the Soviet-imposed government. Karski went on a trip around the world to urge the former government members to send all available documents to Stanford and deposit them at the Hoover Archives.
Karski's papers document two main areas of activity: 1) Collecting activities on behalf of the Hoover Library, and 2) Missions to the Government in Exile during World War II
Karski went on his last top-secret mission across the German territory in 1942 carrying a small suitcase and a microfilm of hundreds of documents. Most of what he conveyed to his superiors in London depended on his amazing ability to memorize dozens of pages and hundreds of names. After he reached his destination safely they were written down. Karski wasn't given access to the documents concerning the publicity surrounding his meetings with influential politicians, journalists or activists until they were opened decades after the war. In the 1980s he visited archival institutions in Europe, Israel and the United States to obtain such copies and incorporate some of their content into this collection. During his trips to Stanford he was presented with documents produced by the Polish government, the agencies he either worked for or was loosely associated with (see list in Related Collections).
In the Hoover collection of Karski's papers the best sources of information on his mission and its aftermath are twenty volumes of scrapbooks. Karski decided to create them in the mid-1980s. His visitors were given the opportunity to come into contact with documents illustrating his biography. It was the donor's wish to keep them in the same order. A visual file, containing audio and video tapes with interviews and documentaries supplements the information in scrapbooks.
Besides a few photographs, very little in Karski's papers concerns his personal life. Later demand for information about his family's background compelled him to reproduce photos depicting his relatives before World War II.
This finding aid was created in 2008 when all of materials Hoover Institution expected to receive were delivered. A register existing before 2008 described the content of the first nine boxes. Since these boxes had been microfilmed the decision was made to keep materials in the same order and not incorporate them into the later acquisitions. Cross references have been provided in the container list.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Sikorski, Władysław, 1881-1943.; Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945); Jews--Poland.; Propaganda, German.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Jews.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.; World War, 1939-1945--Underground movements.; Germany.; Poland.; Poland--History--Occupation, 1939-1945.
Genres and Forms of Material
Phonotapes.; Video tapes.
Related Material
Poland. Ambasada (Great Britain) Records, Hoover Institution Archives
Poland. Ambasada (U.S.) Records, Hoover Institution Archives
Poland. Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych Records, Hoover Institution Archives
Stanislaw Mikolajczyk papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Container List
- Biographical File, 1942-1994. (Box 1-3, 9)
  Correspondence, notes, telegrams, reports on Karski's courier mission to Poland and on his mission to inform the public in the United States and Great Britain. See also scrapbooks.
  Arranged by physical form in boxes 1-3, and alphabetically by subject in box 9
  - Material brought to the Polish government-in-exile in London from Poland by Jan Karski in, 1942
    - "Charakter Misji" (Folder 1: 1)
    - Photographs of typed records (Folder 1: 2)
    - Photographs of Poland under German occupation (activities of the Polish Underground, scenes in the Warsaw Ghetto, etc.) (Folder 1: 3-4)
  - Report given to Gen. Władysław Sikorski in 1943 after Jan Karski arrived in England from Poland (Folder 1: 5-6)
  - Klucz do kryptonimów raportu politycznego Jana Karskiego (key to pseudonyms in Jan Karski's political report) (Folder 1: 5-6)
    - "Obóz Narodowy - Próby konsolidacji" (#1) (Folder 1: 5-6)
    - "Obóz Socjalistyczny" (#2) (Folder 1: 5-6)
    - "Pozycja Stronnictwa Ludowego" (#3) (Folder 1: 5-6)
    - "Unia" (#4) (Folder 1: 5-6)
    - "Ośrodki Ludowo-Demokratyczno-Lewicowe" (#5) (Folder 1: 5-6)
    - "Sanacja" (#6) (Folder 1: 5-6)
    - "Konferencja Okrągłego Stołu" (#7) (Folder 1: 5-6)
    - "Konflikty Życia Podziemnego" (#8) (Folder 1: 5-6)
    - "Siły Zbrojne" (#9) (Folder 1: 5-6)
    - "Delegatura Rządu" (#10) (Folder 1: 5-6)
    - "P.K.P." (#11) (Folder 1: 5-6)
    - "Polityczność Sił Zbrojnych" (#12) (Folder 1: 5-6)
    - "Charakterystyczna Inicjatywa Polityczna" (#13) (Folder 1: 5-6)
    - "Koncepcje Powstania" (#14) (Folder 1: 5-6)
    - "Koncepcje Konsolidacyjne" (#15) (Folder 1: 5-6)
    - "O Kierownictwo Polski Powstańczej" (#16) (Folder 1: 5-6)
    - "Działalność Agentur Sowieckich na Ziemiach Polskich" (#17) (Folder 1: 5-6)
    - "Zagadnienie Łączności" (#18) (Folder 1: 5-6)
    - "Departament Oświaty i Wychowania" (#19) (Folder 1: 5-6)
    - "Państwowy Korpus Bezpieczeństwa" (#20) (Folder 1: 5-6)
    - "Poziom Moralny i Polityczny Życia Podziemnego - Luźne Ośrodki i Ich Rola" (#21) (Folder 1: 5-6)
    - "Zagadnienie Fachowości - Elita - Rola Emigracji" (#22) (Folder 1: 5-6)
    - "Zagadnienie Młodzieży" (#23) (Folder 1: 5-6)
    - "Bierni i 'Współpracujacy' z Okupantem" (#24) (Folder 1: 5-6)
    - "Charakterystyczny Problem 192" (#25) (Folder 1: 5-6)
    - "Prasa Tajna" (#26) (Folder 1: 5-6)
  - Report of Jan Karski to the Prime Minister of the Polish government-in-exile in London on his secret trip to the United States in 1943 and his audience with President Franklin D. Roosevelt (Folder 1: 7)
    - List of prominent people at the secret gathering where Jan Karski gave his report on Poland (Folder 1: 7)
    - Memorandum for the Prime Minister (personal) (Folder 1: 7)
    - Memorandum of conversation between Jan Karski and prominent Americans (Folder 1: 7)
    - Memorandum of discussion between J. Kwaśniewski and prominent Americans and Englishmen (Folder 1: 7)
    - Report from conversation during an audience with President Franklin D. Roosevelt (Folder 1: 7)
    - Report no. 1 of Jan Karski's activities during his first trip to the United States (4 copies) (Folder 1: 7)
    - Report no. 2 of Jan Karski's activities during his first secret trip to the United States, 1943 (Folder 1: 7)
    - Report no. 3 from Jan Karski's secret mission to the United States, "The Jewish Problem" (Folder 1: 7)
    - Report no. 3, "Reakcje kluczowych osobistości amerykańskich na mój referat" (Folder 1: 7)
    - Report no. 4 of Jan Karski's secret visit to the United States, 1943, "Spostrzeżenia i Wnioski" (Folder 1: 7)
    - Report from Jan Karski's secret trip to the United States in 1943, "Do Pana Kierownika Spraw Zagranicznych przy Delegacie Rządu" (Folder 1: 7)
  - Jan Karski's report on the activities of the Polish Underground up to 1943 in the fight against the German occupation (Folder 2: 1)
    - "Prasa Tajna" (#1) (Folder 2: 1)
    - "Podtrzymywanie Nastroju Walki w Społeczeństwie Polskim" (#2) (Folder 2: 1)
    - "Życie w Polsce" (#3) (Folder 2: 1)
    - "Ogólny Charakter Ruchu Podziemnego" (#4) (Folder 2: 1)
    - "Sytuacja Żywnościowa" (#5) (Folder 2: 1)
    - "Charakter Polskiego Ruchu Podziemnego" (#6) (Folder 2: 1)
    - "Prasa Tajna" (Ciąg dalszy) (#7) (Folder 2: 1)
    - "The Construction of the Polish Underground Movement" (#8) (Folder 2: 1)
    - "Material do Memorandum" (#9) (Folder 2: 1)
    - "Życie w Polsce" (#10) (Folder 2: 1)
    - "Polski Ruch Podziemny" (#11) (Folder 2: 1)
    - "Pytania i Odpowiedzi" (#12) (Folder 2: 1)
    - "Kraj i Emigracja" (#13) (Folder 2: 1)
    - "The Organization of the Underground Movement in Poland" (#14) (Folder 2: 1)
    - "Organizacja Ruchu Podziemnego w Polsce" (#15) (Folder 2: 1)
    - Państwo Polskie No. 12 from 1943 April 23 (#16) (Folder 2: 1)
    - Artykuł P. J. Nowaka wygłoszony w House of Commons (#17) (Folder 2: 1)
    - "O Ile Można Stwierdzić Prawdziwość Oskarżeń Zawartych w Prawdzie"(#18) (Folder 2: 1)
    - Sprawozdanie z działalności propagandowej Jana Karskiego o sprawach krajowych w czasie od 10 1943 roku do 1 lutego 1944 roku (#19) (Folder 2: 1)
    - "Lista Nazwisk w Ruchu Podziemnym" (#20) (Folder 2: 2)
    - "Raport z Misji Jana Karskiego w roku 1940" (#21) (Folder 2: 2)
    - Introductory letters - Jan Karski's second trip to the United States (#22) (Folder 2: 2)
    - Memorandum of discussion between Jan Karski and prominent Americans and Englishmen, London, 1943 (#23) (Folder 2: 2)
    - Report no. 1 from Jan Karski's trip to the United States (#24) (Folder 2: 2)
    - Memorandum of Jan Karski's discussion with English politicians and reporters (#25) (Folder 2: 2)
    - Report no. 4 from Jan Karski's trip to the United States (#26) (Folder 2: 2)
    - Loose pages of information on Poles during World War II (#27) (Folder 2: 2)
    - "Egzamin Wstępny" by Zygmunt Nagórski, Jr. (#28) (Folder 2: 2)
    - "Amerykańska Produkcja Filmowa i Zagadnienie Filmu Polskiego" by Ryszard Ordyński, 1943 December 27 (#29) (Folder 2: 2)
    - Uwagi Wincentego Bejtmana, kierownika Wydziału Filmowego w sprawie projektowanej produkcji filmów pełnometrażowych w Hollywood (#30) (Folder 2: 2)
    - "Podziemne Państwo Polskie - Charatker Ruchu Podziemnego" (#31) (Folder 2: 2)
    - Notatka dla Pana Premiera - "Partyzanci Sowieccy" (#32) (Folder 2: 2)
    - "Warunki Egzystencji Ludnosci Polskiej na Terenach Inkorporowanych" (#33) (Folder 2: 2)
    - "Niebezpieczeństwo Zagrażające Ludności Polskiej" (#34) (Folder 2: 2)
    - Memorandum to Minister Tadeusz Romer, 1943 October 4 (#35) (Folder 2: 2)
    - Proposed interview (#36) (Folder 2: 2)
    - Proposed letter to P. Kestner - Protest (#37) (Folder 2: 2)
    - Rezolucja (#38) (Folder 2: 2)
    - "Le mouvement souterrain en Pologne" (#39) (Folder 2: 2)
    - "Polski Ruch Podziemny" (#40) (Folder 2: 3)
    - "Wiadomości Gospodarcze i Finansowe" (#41)
    - Notatka dla Pana Ministra T. Romera (#42) (Folder 2: 3)
    - "Inside Poland Today" by Leon Dennen (#43) (Folder 2: 3)
    - Notatka dla Pana Premiera (#44) (Folder 2: 3)
    - "Niemcy na Przyszlość - Mentalność Młodzieży Niemieckiej" (#45) (Folder 2: 3)
    - Ramowe Przemowienie na temat Stosunków Polsko-Rosyjskich (#46) (Folder 2: 3)
    - Notatka dla Pana Ministra Banaczyka (#47) (Folder 2: 3)
    - Notatka dla Pana Dyrektora Paprockiego (Min. Spraw Wewn.) (#48) (Folder 2: 3)
    - "Działalność Agentur Sowieckich na Ziemiach Polskich" (#49) (Folder 2: 3)
    - Notatka dla Pana Ministra J. Kwapinskiego (#50) (Folder 2: 3)
    - "The Polish Underground Front and Russian Relations" (#51) (Folder 2: 3)
    - "Washington Receptus 374" (#52) (Folder 2: 3)
    - "Panu Premierowi pro Memoria," London, 1943 October 5 (#53) (Folder 2: 3)
    - Notatka dla Pana Premiera, 1943 October 5 (#54) (Folder 2: 3)
    - Notatka dla Pana Premiera, 1943 February 11 (#55) (Folder 2: 3)
    - "Akcja Partyzantów Sowieckich w Polsce" (#56) (Folder 2: 3)
    - "Prasa Tajna" (#57) (Folder 2: 3)
    - Notatka, London, 1943 September 28 (#58) (Folder 2: 3)
    - "Polska bez Quislinga" (#59) (Folder 2: 3)
    - Individual reports, 1943 September 9 (#60) (Folder 2: 3)
    - Przemówienie Wice-Premiera - Pana Stanisława Mikołajczyka, 1943 May 13 (#61) (Folder 2: 3)
    - Pytania w Sprawach Krajowych (#62) (Folder 2: 4)
    - Komunikaty, London, 1943 February 23 (#63) (Folder 2: 4)
    - "Do Delegata Rządu, do Wiadomości Dyrektorów Departamentów Komendanta S.Z., PKP, oraz Patriotycznych Ośrodków i Wybitniejszych Osób Życia Podziemnego" (#64) (Folder 2: 4)
    - "Roman - Dyrektor Biura" (#65) (Folder 2: 4)
    - "Pilecki lub jego Żona - Departament Spraw Wewnętrznych" (#66) (Folder 2: 4)
    - "Rodacy" (#67) (Folder 2: 4)
    - Notatka dla Rządu Polskiego - Dotyczy misji Jana Karskiego w Londynie (#68) (Folder 2: 4)
    - Notatka dla Profesora Kota, London, 1943 April 13 (#69) (Folder 2: 4)
    - Depesza w sprawie oficerów (#70) (Folder 2: 4)
    - Luźne (#71) (Folder 2: 4)
    - Projekt przemówienia - "Polacy" (#72) (Folder 2: 4)
    - Notatka w sprawach kościoła w Polsce (#73) (Folder 2: 4)
    - Kwestionariusz (#74) (Folder 2: 4)
    - "Discours prononcé par le General Sikorski le 28 janvier 1943" (#75) (Folder 2: 4)
    - Notatka dla Pana Eydziatowicza (#76) (Folder 2: 4)
    - Wykaz materiałów krajowych (photocopies) (#77) (Folder 2: 4)
    - Załącznik No. 1 (#78) (Folder 2: 4)
    - "Szaniec Bolesławów" (#79) (Folder 2: 4)
    - "Staszek" (#80) (Folder 2: 4)
    - "Polskie Życie Organizacyjne Podziemne" (#81) (Folder 2: 4)
    - "Wiadomości Gospodarcze i Finansowe" (#82) (Folder 2: 4)
    - "O Kierownictwo Polski Powstańczej" (#83) (Folder 2: 4)
    - "Działalność Agentur Sowieckich na Ziemiach Polskch" (#84) (Folder 2: 4)
    - "Podział z Punktu Widzenia Politycznego" (#85) (Folder 2: 4)
  - Press clippings about Story of the Secret State by Jan Karski (Folder 2: 5-6)
  - Press clippings about Story of the Secret State by Jan Karski (Folder 3: 1-3)
  - Supplement to The Polish Review (#1) (Folder 3: 4)
  - Two indexes to Poland Fights (#2)
  - "Zagadnienie Granic w Świetle Cywilizacji" by Seweryn Kamieński (border problems in the light of civilization) (#3) (Folder 3: 5)
  - "Vademecum w Sprawach Polskich" - Manuscript written by an anonymous author of Poland during the German occupation (#4) (Folder 3: 6)
  - Explanatory notes to Dumbarton Oaks proposals (#5) (Folder 3: 7)
  - Winston Churchill's speech in the House of Commons, 1944 February 27 (#6) (Folder 3: 7)
  - Introductory remarks - Agreement concerning Poland reached by the Three Powers at the Crimean Conference, 1945 February 14 (#7) (Folder 3: 7)
  - "The Truth About Poland" by a New Zealander who just got out, P. R. Earle (#8) (Folder 3: 7)
  - Polish Catholic Agency's Bulletin, issued under the Warsaw regime auspices (#9) (Folder 3: 7)
  - A declaration of the Związek Obrony Niepodległości Polski (United Committee of Independence of Poland) (#10) (Folder 3: 7)
  - Leaflet issued by the Polish Underground Resistance in Poland regarding the Moscow trial of Polish underground leaders (#11) (Folder 3: 7)
  - Miscellany (Folder 3: 8)
  - Charitable donations, 1985-1986 (Folder 9: 1)
  - Mission in 1942
    - Article about Karski's mission, 1945 (Folder 9: 2)
    - Yad Vashem archival materials (Folder 9: 3)
  - Activities and structure of the Polish Underground. Report for Sikorski, 1943 (Folder 9: 4)
  - British and American officials. Correspondence with, 1942-1945 (Folder 9: 5)
  - Concentration camps in occupied Poland, July 1942.; Typescript in English (Folder 9: 6)
  - Chronology of trip through Europe in, 1942 (Folder 9: 7)
    - Undated typescript (Folder 9: 8)
  - Great Britain
    - General, 1943 (Folder 9: 8)
    - General, 1944 (Folder 9: 9)
    - British reaction to information on extermination of Jews, 1942 (Folder 9: 10)
    - Detention by British authorities, 1942 (Folder 9: 11)
    - Talks with politicians and journalists, 1943-1944 (Folder 9: 12)
  - Mission to France. Moja pierwsza misja do Francji. Undated notes (Folder 9: 13)
  - Polish government telegrams from various stages of Karski's trip, 1942 (Folder 9: 14)
  - Political report on conditions in Poland, January 1943 (Folder 9: 15)
  - United States
    - General, 1943-1944 (Folder 9: 16)
    - Activities as described by other authors, 1943-1944 (Folder 9: 17)
  - Trips, 1966-1994
    - Asia and Africa, September 1966-March 1967 (Folder 9: 18)
    - Israel, 1981-1994
      - General, 1981-1982 (Folder 9: 19)
      - Honorary citizenship, 1994 (Folder 9: 20)
- Correspondence, 1944-1998. (Box 9-10)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - General
    - General, 1985-1996 (Folder 9: 21)
    - Assistance to Poles in Poland and abroad, 1945. (Folder 9: 22)
      Includes letters from and to Zofia Kossak- Szczucka
    - Letters of appreciation, 1951-1969 (Folder 9: 23-24)
    - Letters of appreciation, 1970-1993 (Folder 10: 1-3)
  - Bieńkowski, Witold, 1944 (Folder 10: 4)
  - Czekalski, Marek, 1998 (Folder 10: 5)
  - Georgetown University Library, 1982-1984 (Folder 10: 6)
  - Giedroyć, Jerzy, 1982-1986 (Folder 10: 7)
  - Herling-Grudziński, Gustaw, 1945 (Folder 10: 8)
  - Hodges, Robert H, 1993 (Folder 10: 9)
  - Hoover Library and Archives, 1945-1946 (Folder 10: 10-12)
  - Lerski, Jerzy, 1945 (Folder 10: 13)
  - Sobkowicz, G., 1989-1993 (Folder 10: 14)
  - Washington Embassy of Poland, 1944-1946 (Folder 10: 15-17)
- Government-in-Exile Records, 1941-1946. (Box 11)
  Bulletins, circulars, reports, statements and interviews.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject
  - General
    - Bulletins
      - Biuletyn Własnego Nasłuchu Radiowego, 1945 July (Folder 11: 1)
      - Informacje Ogólne, 1946 (Folder 11: 2)
      - Raport o Sytuacji w Polsce, 1941, 1945 (Folder 11: 3)
    - Circulars, 1944-1945 (Folder 11: 4)
    - Reports. Liberation Russian Style, 1944 (Folder 11: 5)
  - Armed Forces
    - Dowództwo SiłPowietrznych. Biuletyn Informacyjny, 1945 (Folder 11: 6)
    - Poland's Defense Potentials (Potencjał Obronny Polski), 1943 (Folder 11: 7)
  - German press and radio monitoring, April-May 1945 (Folder 11: 8)
  - Mikołajczyk, Stanisław. Miscellaneous statements and interviews, 1942-1944 (Folder 11: 9)
  - Ministry of Information
    - Review of articles on Poland in the British press, 1944, 1946 (Folder 11: 10)
    - Wiadomości Krajowe, 1947 (Folder 11: 11)
    - Znaczenie Gospodarcze Ziem Odzyskanych, 1946 (Folder 11: 12)
  - Ministry of Interior.Życie Gospodarcze Polski w Okresie Przedwojenym, 1944 (Folder 11: 13)
  - Polish Government Information Center-United States, 1944-1945 (Folder 11: 14)
  - Soviet rule in Poland, 1944 (Folder 11: 15)
  - United Nations Conference, San Francisco. Polish protest, June 1945 (Folder 11: 16)
  - Zaleski, August. Statement before the National Council, July 29, 1940 (Folder 11: 17)
- Interviews, 1992-1996. (Box 12)
  Published interviews with Jan Karski. See also scrapbooks.
  - General, 1992-1996 (Folder 12: 1)
  - Jan Karski with Plater Robinson, undated (Folder 12: 2)
- Speeches and Writings, 1944-1997. (Box 12)
  Articles, correspondence and speeches. See also Scrapbooks.
  Arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Articles. Poland, Life Magazine, 1944 August 28 (Folder 12: 3)
  - Books
    - The Great Powers. Correspondence, 1982-1990
      - Chojecki, Mirosław, 1985-1988 (Folder 12: 4)
      - Morawiec, Elżbieta, 1982-1990 (Folder 12: 5)
    - Secret State
      - General, 1944-1945 (Folder 12: 6)
      - Najder, Zdzisław and Najder Carroll, Halina, 1981-1986 (Folder 12: 7)
      - Press reviews, 1944 (Folder 12: 8)
    - Warsaw Uprising - government book proposal, 1945 (Folder 12: 9)
  - Speeches
    - Committee on Foreign Affairs, House of Representatives, 1962 (Folder 12: 10)
    - King's College, March 31 1995 (Folder 12: 11)
    - Washington, January 16 1997 (Folder 12: 12)
- Subject File, 1941-1997. (Box 12-13)
  Typescripts, bulletins, speeches, telegrams and theater play script.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - British League for European Freedom. Flyers, 1945 (Folder 12: 13)
  - Brzeski, Tadeusz. Historic essays, 1943 (Folder 12: 14)
  - Dumbarton Oaks Conference Proposals, 1944 (Folder 12: 15)
  - Émigrés. Social and political life, 1945-1951
    - General, 1945-1951 (Folder 12: 16)
    - Academicus, 1945 (Folder 12: 17)
  - Gerson, Louis, L, The Reaction of the Polish Government-in-Exile and the Allied Governments to the News of the Endloesung. Typescript, 1988 (Folder 12: 18)
  - Great Britain. House of Commons. Debate on Churchill's speech on Poland from, December 15, 1944 (Folder 12: 19)
  - Lednicki, Wacław, Russian - Polish relations, 1943 (Folder 12: 20)
  - Perel, Solomon, Europa, Europa, typescript, 1997 (Folder 12: 21)
  - Polish - Americans. Internet discussion. Printout, 1997 (Folder 12: 22)
  - Polish-Jewish relations. Historic essays, 1945-1989 (Folder 12: 23)
  - Polish Publications Committee - Bulletins, undated, 1941-1945 (Folder 13: 1)
  - Polish underground communist press, 1944 (Folder 13: 2)
  - Polish women's contribution to the war, 1945 (Folder 13: 3)
  - Polski Ruch Niepodległosciowy Niepodległosc i Demokracja, 1945-1946 (Folder 13: 4)
  - Scharf, Rafael. Speech, 1993 (Folder 13: 5)
  - Raczkiewicz, Władysław. Speeches on anniversaries of the outbreak of World War II, 1942-1944 (Folder 13: 6)
  - Sosnkowski, Kazimierz, January 13 1945 (Folder 13: 7)
  - United States State Department. Documents related to Poland, 1940-1942 (Folder 13: 8)